# Diego Alburez-Gutierrez

Konrad-Zuse-Straße 1, 18057 Rostock, Germany alburezgutierrez@demogr.mpg.de; www.alburez.me

I am a social scientist specialising in inter-generational demography. My work has used mathematical modeling, micro-simulation techniques, and empirical analysis to explore changes in the experience of life events such as kin availability, family bereavement, and caring responsibilities across demographic regimes.

### AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

- 2019 Otto Hahn Medal (2020) awarded by the Max Planck Society for 'outstanding achievement from the initial creative period of young scientists', in particular 'for methodological innovations for studying the long-term consequences of mass killings on local populations'
- LSE PhD Academy Prize (2018) awarded by the London School of Economics for research on statesponsored massacres in Guatemala
- LSE PhD Studentship (2014-2018) awarded by the London School of Economics

#### **EDUCATION**

## The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

PhD, Demography and Population Studies

2014 - 2018

- Summary: Effects of mass violence and genocide on population dynamics.
- Data collection: Genealogical surveys and in-depth interviews (1 year fieldwork)
- Mixed methods research design:
  - Quantitative analysis: Descriptive demographic, regression and survival models, network analysis
  - Qualitative analysis: Thematic and framework analysis
- Supervisors: Arjan Gjonça, Tiziana Leone, Ernestina Coast, and Michael Murphy

MSc, Social Research Methods (Distinction)

2013-2014

Practical approach with emphasis on quantitative and qualitative data analysis

## Del Valle University, Guatemala

BA, Anthropology (First class)

2008-2012

Thesis on evaluation methodologies for Conditional Cash Transfer Programmes

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany

Research Scientist (post-doc) and Research Area Chair (Aging and Generational Processes), Lab of Digital and Computational Demography

Since 2018
Leading role in projects using innovative data and approaches to understand demographic change in the context of global population aging.

## United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), Denmark

Statistics Team Intern, Field Information and Coordination Support Section (FICSS) Central role in implementing UNHCR's Demographic Projection Tool.

2018

The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK Research Assistant, Law Department Leading qualitative research on low student satisfaction	2017
Research Assistant, Social Policy Department Quantitative analysis of maternal and child health outcomes in Palestine	2016-2017
Research Assistant, Sociology Department Qualitative coding and analysis of methodological practices in sociology of work	2014-2015
Research Assistant, Methodology Department Survey of grey literature to identify common qualitative methods in International Development	2013-2014
Public Opinion Program, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala Lead researcher Designing and implementing qualitative research for the Media Monitoring Project	2013
<ul> <li>The Population Council, Guatemala</li> <li>Research Sub Coordinator</li> <li>Design and implementation of qualitative research on conditional cash transfer programm</li> <li>Led team of four ethnographers during six months of data collection in rural Guatemala</li> </ul>	2012 nes
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
European Doctoral School of Demography (EDSD), Barcelona Class Teacher for course "Digital Demography" Online due to COVID-19; materials and recorded lectures available on GitHub	2020
<ul> <li>The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK</li> <li>Class Teacher, Social Policy Department</li> <li>Leading seminars for the course "Introduction to Global Population Change"</li> <li>Weekly office hours, updated course website, homework and exam marking</li> </ul>	2016-2017
Class Teacher, LSE Methods Summer School  • Leading seminars for the "Qualitative Research Methods" strand  • Homework and exam marking	2015
<ul> <li>Del Valle University, Guatemala</li> <li>Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department</li> <li>Leading seminars for the course "Advanced qualitative data analysis"</li> <li>Course design, wrote NVivo course pack (Spanish), homework and exam marking</li> </ul>	2013
Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department	2011

# OTHER PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Plaza Pública Newspaper, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala

Leading seminars for the course "History of Anthropology 1"

Data journalist 2013

In charge of database management for data journalism focusing on local politics. Co-authored several publications.

## iDISC Information Technologies, Spain/Guatemala

Language moderator for translation of Microsoft Office 2013 to K'iche' Mayan

2012-2013

- In charge of recruitment, linguistics, and project management
- Led team of six translating the MS Office Language Interface Pack 2013 K'iche'

#### PUBLICATIONS IN PEER-REVIEWED JOURNALS

- Nepomuceno, M., Acosta, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Aburto, J.M., Gagnon, A., and Turra, C. (Forthcoming). "Besides population age-structure, health and other demographic factors can contribute to understanding the COVID-19 burden across the globe." Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (Accepted for publication).
- Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Chandrasekharan, E., Chunara, R., Gil-Clavel, S., Hannak, A., Interdonato, R., Joseph, K., Kalimeri, K., Malik, M., Mayer, K., Mejova, Y., Paolotti, D., and Zagheni, E. (2019). "Reports of the Workshops Held at the 2019 International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media." AI Magazine, 40(4), 78-82. doi:10.1609/aimag.v40i4.5287.
- Leone, T., Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Gandour, R., Coast, E., and Giacaman, R. (2019). "Maternal and child access to care and intensity of conflict in the occupied Palestinian territory: a pseudo-longitudinal analysis (2000–2014)." Conflict and Health 13(1). doi:10.1186/s13031-019-0220-2.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (2019). Blood is thicker than bloodshed: A genealogical approach to reconstruct populations after armed conflicts. Demographic Research, 40(23): 627-656. doi:10.4054/DemRes.2019.40.23.
- McGovern, P., and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez**. (2017) "Who takes workplace case-study methods seriously? The influence of gender, academic rank and PhD training." Industrial Relations Journal 48(2):98-114, doi:10.1111/irj.12171.

#### **BOOK CHAPTERS**

Alburez-Gutierrez, D., S. Aref, S. Gil-Clavel, A. Grow, D.V. Negraia, E. Zagheni. (2019). "Demography in the Digital Era: New Data Sources for Population Research." Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the Italian Statistical Society. doi: 10.31235/osf.io/24jp7.

## TECHNICAL REPORTS

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** and Segura Garcia, C. (2018). "The UNHCR Demographic Projection Tool: estimating the future size and composition of forcibly displaced populations." UNHCR Statistics Technical Series, 2018/1.

#### WORKING PAPERS AND PAPERS IN PROGRESS

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, E. Zagheni and M. Kolk. (November 2019) "Women's experience of child death: a global demographic perspective". SocArxiv. doi: 10.31235/osf.io/s69fz.

- Smith-Greenway, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Zagheni, E. and Trinitapoli, J. (in progress) "Global Burden of Maternal Bereavement: A Worldwide Analysis of Maternal Cumulative Prevalence of Child Mortality".
- Williams, I. and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez** (in progress) "A formal demographic approach to child survival from a mother's perspective: mortality change and related measures".
- **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (April 2020). "Mass killings, family support, and survival: evidence from Guatemala".
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (January 2020). "Fertility and pronatalism among massacre survivors in Mayan Guatemala".

## INVITED PRESENTATIONS (SELECTED)

- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (27 May 2020, postponed due to Covid-19 lockdown) "Die demografischen Auswirkungen von Massengewalt in Guatemala [The demographic consequences of Genocide in Guatemala]." Berlin, Germany (Ibero-American Institute).
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (27 Nov 2019) "Women's experience of child death: a global demographic perspective." ISER External Seminar, Colchester, UK (Institute for Social and Economic Research, University of Essex).
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (23 May 2019) "The Demographic Foundations of the Lived Experience of Kin Death: A Genealogical Reconstruction." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University).
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (25 April 2019) "Ciencias Sociales Computacionales: Retos y oportunidades en la era digital [Computational Social Sciences: challenges and opportunities in the Digital Age]". Guatemala City, Guatemala (Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences).
- Alburez-Gutierrez, D. (8 February 2018) "Mass killings, family support, and survival: evidence from Guatemala." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University).

## OUTREACH AND SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

- Academic video: 'How Can We Quantify the Immediate and Lingering Impact of Genocide on Local Populations?' (Latest Thinking, Apr 2020)
- Opinion piece: 'Coronavirus: a warning to Latin America and the Caribbean to dramatically increase COVID-19 testing' (The Conversation, UK, Apr 2020)
- Blog post: 'Genocide is the tip of the iceberg: Reviewing the Guatemalan case' (LSE Human Rights Blog, Feb 2016)

## **SKILLS**

- Statistical programming: R (base, tidyverse, data.table, parallel, shiny), Stata, Excel
- Text processing and web: LaTeX, MS Office, (r)markdown, HTML, JavaScript, Tesseract
- Other programming: Git, Python 3, SQL, Hadoop

- Demographic microsimulation: SOCSIM with applications in R
- Qualitative data analysis: NVivo, Atlas.ti
- Experience in qualitative, quantitative, and online data collection

## **LANGUAGES**

- International: **Spanish** (native), **English** (full professional C2), **German** (full professional C1), **Swedish** (beginner A1)
- Guatemalan/Mexican: **K'iche'** (full professional C1), **Achi** (full professional C1), **Kaqchikel** (professional B1), **Q'eqchi'** (limited working A2)

## ORGANISER OF INTERNATIONAL ACADEMIC EVENTS

- Organiser: Rostock Open Science Workshop, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Rostock 2019
- Organiser: Workshop on Demographic Research with Web and Social Media Data, 13<sup>th</sup> International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), Munich

# SERVICE TO THE DISCIPLINE

- Reviewer for academic journals: Demography; Journal of Marriage and Family; Demographic Research; Revue Quetelet/Quetelet Journal; 11<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Social Informatics (SocInfo '19)
- Expert witness for US asylum cases at the 'Center for Gender & Refugee Studies' Since 2018
- Organiser of the 'Social Policy Qualitative Research Group', London School of Economics 2017-2018
- President of the 'Methodology Student Union', London School of Economics 2013-2014
- President of the 'Social Sciences Student Union', Del Valle University (Guatemala) 2011-2012

#### PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP)
- British Society for Population Studies (BSPS)
- Population Association of America (PAA)
- Latin American Studies Association (LASA)
- Households in Conflict Network (HiCN)
- International Science, Technology, and Innovation Network of Guatemala (REDCTI)